<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A verie godlie and learned sermon treating of mans mortalitie, and of the estate both of his bodie and soule after death. Preached at Denham in Suffolke. At the celebration of the solemne and mournfull funerals of the right orshipfull Sir Edward Lewkenor Knight, and of the vertuous Ladie Susan, his wife, both at once. By M. Robert Pricke their beloued and faithfull minister: now also since that time (to the encrease of our sorow for the losse of so excellent a light) departed this life.</title>
            <author>Pricke, Robert, d. ca. 1608.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1608</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 84 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10084</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20338</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112476</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847726</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847726</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12784</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10084)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12784)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1608:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A verie godlie and learned sermon treating of mans mortalitie, and of the estate both of his bodie and soule after death. Preached at Denham in Suffolke. At the celebration of the solemne and mournfull funerals of the right orshipfull Sir Edward Lewkenor Knight, and of the vertuous Ladie Susan, his wife, both at once. By M. Robert Pricke their beloued and faithfull minister: now also since that time (to the encrease of our sorow for the losse of so excellent a light) departed this life.</title>
                  <author>Pricke, Robert, d. ca. 1608.</author>
                  <author>Allen, Robert, fl. 1596-1612.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[46] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Creede,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1608.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Editor's dedication signed: Robert Allen.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴ 2A²  B-E⁴ F²  (-A1).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lewkenor, Edward, --  Sir, d. 1605.</term>
               <term>Lewkenor, Susan, --  Lady, d. 1605.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12784:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A VERIE GODLIE and Learned Sermon, treating of Mans mortalitie, <hi>and of the eſtate both of his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die and ſoule after death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Preached at Denham in Suffolke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AT The celebration of the ſolemne and mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>funerals of the right worſhipfull</hi> Sir Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Lewkenor <hi>Knight, and of the vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> Ladie <hi>Suſan,</hi> his wife, both at once.</p>
            <p>By <hi>M. Robert Pricke,</hi> their beloued and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Miniſter: now alſo ſince that time (to <hi>the encreaſe of our ſorow for the loſſe of ſo</hi> excellent a light) departed this life.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Man goeth to the houſe of his age: and the mourners goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout in the ſtreete.</p>
               <bibl>Eccleſ. <hi>12.5.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Yet,</p>
            <q>
               <p>Christians must not mourne as other which haue no hope.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1.</hi> Theſſ. <hi>4.13.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>For,</p>
            <q>
               <p>To be looſened and to bee with Christ, is beſt of all.</p>
               <bibl> Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip. <hi>1.23.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by Thomas Creede. 1608.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:12784:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12784:2"/>
            <head>¶ To my louing friend M. <hi>Timothie Pricke,</hi> Miniſter of the word of God, heartie Salutation in the Lord.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y welbeloued, and verie deare friend in the Lord: as God of his great good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and aboundant mercie hath vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafed you no ſmall fauour, in that you are not onely the naturall ſonne of a good man, but alſo the ſonne of a verie faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Miniſter of his holy word, thereby alſo a ſpirituall Father vnto you in the Goſpell of Ieſus Chriſt; euen to you a ſonne of his beſt deſires, and moſt comfortable hope, an heire to manie his earneſt prayers<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſupplications to God, a behoulder &amp; witnes of his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie life, a ſheepe of his deare flocke, and nowe a paſtor of thoſe who were lately his ſheepe: ſo I beſeech you for the Lords ſake, to indeuour after no ſmall and vulgar fruits of dutie and thankes to God your heauenly Father; nor of imitation in reſpect of the excellent vertues of your both naturall and ſpirituall Father.</p>
            <p>Lay ſure and faſt hold, I pray you, on the bleſsing of his holie &amp; feruent prayers, wherein with great wreſtlings, he intreated God often, that hee would make you an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of greater glorie to him, in foyling the diuell, and furthering the ſaluation of his people much more then hee thought himſelfe to haue attained vnto: though in truth hee quitted himſelfe exceedinglie well, and greatlie pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpered in that ſpirituall fight and dangerous battell, and in promoting the ſaluation of verie manie.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:12784:3"/>
Thus comfort you vs deare friend, the deare and louing friendes of your worthy Father: thus reioice you the hearts of Gods people: and thus te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der the good peace of your owne conſcience I heartely intreat you. Where much hath ben beſtowed, there much may iuſtly bee looked for: and therefore as good ground hauing receiued the beſt ſeede, yeeld you your beſt endeuor that you may bring foorth fruite after the fulleſt meaſure euen to an hundred fold. A<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mong other prouocations and incouragements let the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent <hi>Sermon</hi> of your Father be as the lift of a ſtrong ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to further you (as longe as you ſhall liue) in the care of a godly life as he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtantly liued: that growing to like per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection and ripenes of all holy miniſtery, you may after ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>y yeares dy the like death of the righteous that he died.</p>
            <p>In the meane ſeaſon, giue me leaue to commend it vnto you, as a moſt artificiall picture, better repreſenting to the view of your inward ſight, the ſpiritual image of your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: then any the ſkilfulleſt <hi>Limmer</hi> could haue drawne his outward ſhape, to the beholding of your bodilie eye.</p>
            <p>Eſteeme it, deare friend, as a verie worthy and memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable monument of that pure and pithie manner of prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching which he vſed: and as a notable preſident ſet before you, and before vs all; let vs follow it with as proſperous a purſuite as we may. And if we cannot attaine vnto it: yet let vs preſſe toward it as neare as we can. Wee all knowe what a bleſſing God gaue to his ſincere and faithfull dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling: that is, ſo plentifull a bleſſing, as is ſeldo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e to be ſeene vpon the miniſterie of any in a far greater congregation.</p>
            <p>Now further, that which remaineth: ioine with me in requeſt to the right worſhipfull, to whom your Father did, both with hand and heart, while yet hee was liuing, dedicate this memorable gift, (a teſtimony of his ſpeciall loue, from a moſt parentlike and paſtorall affection to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward them) that they will accept it as one little ſiluer ſtrea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e, of pure and precious water, deriued vnto them from that more full and liuing ſpringe, which was wont to flow dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie
<pb facs="tcp:12784:3"/>more plenteouſly, to the ſweete refreſhing and comfort<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ting of their ſoules. And albeit his perſon be now gone, and his paſtorall care ouer them hath had an end, (which if they had continued to this day, would ſurely haue procured their moſt ready and thankfull accepting of the ſame) let vs be ſutors, that the thing it ſelfe being of great worth, may be neuer the leſſe regarded of them: remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring ſtill that they muſt giue an account vnto God, how they haue profited by his holy miniſtery. In which hope, let vs for concluſion, (omitting all complements wanting) beſeech God the only full ſupplier of all defects: to bleſſe the holy doctrine of this one bleſſed <hi>Sermon,</hi> to as manie good endes and purpoſes, both to them, and to our ſelues, and to many other, as any one <hi>Sermon</hi> may be bleſſed and ſanctified vnto.</p>
            <p>And thus with my moſt hearty prayer, I doe commend both your ſelfe, and that right worſhipfull familie, and all of the families of the Church of God, at your and their little <hi>Denham,</hi> to all further and more full bleſsing of God.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your louing friend and brother in the Lord. <hi>ROBERT ALLEN.</hi>
               </signed> 
               <dateline>
                  <hi>London,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>this</hi> 2. <hi>of May.</hi> 1608.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:12784:4"/>
            <head>To the right vvorshipfull and Chriſtian poſteritie, the Sonnes and <hi>Daughters of the right worſhipfull</hi> Sir Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Lewkenor <hi>Knight, and of the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Ladie</hi> Suſan Lewkenor <hi>his wife.</hi> Grace and peace in Chriſt Ieſus.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> by the motion of Gods <hi>holie ſpirit,</hi> did long ſince in great zeale vtter this holy ſaying. <hi>The righteous periſheth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57.1.</note> 
               <hi>and no man conſidereth it in heart, and mercifull men are taken away, and no man vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstandeth that the righteous is taken away from the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill to come.</hi> Which, as it hath in former times bene true, ſo is it prooued moſt true in theſe our miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and deſperate daies: as may hereby appeare, for that although the Lord withdraweth and taketh out of this world by death many of his principall and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent ſeruants, thereby ſetting vp (as it were) prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Comets, to premoniſh all men not only of the vncertainty of this natural life, but alſo that his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are neare hand: yet few doe ſo much as once turne their eyes toward this hand of God; and few<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er doe make vſe thereof, and applie it to their heart, for the increaſe of true godlineſſe and reformation of life.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:12784:4"/>
Againſt which eſtate &amp; diſpoſition graceleſſe, and more then brutiſh, ſome what was vttered at the Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall of your ſaid worthie Parents: which although it hath hetherto lyen in ſilence, and beene whollie ſuppreſſed, yet nowe by the grace of God it is come to light.</p>
            <p>The diſcourſe (I confeſſe) is homely &amp; rude: and the rather, becauſe that in the extreame colde when it was deliuered, the naturall inſtruments and partes of the Preacher, did performe their duties not ſo wel as at other times. But ſeeing it doth containe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the plaine &amp; ſimple truth, there is no cauſe whie it ſhould feare the curioſitie of proude carpers, and deprauers. Whatſoeuer it bee, I doe heere pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent it to you all ioyntlie, and that for diuers reaſons.</p>
            <p>The firſt is, in regard of the manifolde benefites and fauours, which I and mine haue enioyed both from your ſelues, and at the hands of your ſaide de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed Parents: which becauſe I can in no wiſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite, I content my ſelfe with this ſlender ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thankfullnes (following therein the example of manie in all times, who haue by ſmall gifts, as of a roote, or water taken vp in the hollowe of the hand, expreſſed their loue, and diſpatched dutie towards great perſons) and doe by prayer commit a fuller re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compenſe to bee made by him who hath promiſed not to forget a cup of colde water beſtowed vpon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of his.</p>
            <p>Secondlie, for that the treatiſe doth not onely put you in minde of your fraile and mortall condition,
<pb facs="tcp:12784:5"/>euen nowe in this your youthfull and flouriſhing e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate; that ſo you might walke in feare, and euerie houre fitte your ſelues for the Lordes calling of you away by death: but alſo containeth, or rather brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie toucheth diuers neceſſarie pointes of Chriſtian doctrine and religion: which may ſerue as a remedie againſt the horrible prophaneneſſe, Atheiſme, and contempt of GOD, which (as ſome great floud) doth at this time, ouerflow the bancks of this whole Land.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, to ſtirre you vp (although forward of your ſelues) to followe and treade in the holie ſteppes of your worthy Parents gone before: the traces wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, are in this <hi>Sermon</hi> trulie and faithfully ſet downe, without all flatterie or oſtentation.</p>
            <p>They were both of them carefull in their life to prouide for your good and happy eſtate, both in this life, and the life to come. If therefore you ſhall after their death, runne on in the courſe of <hi>righteouſnes,</hi> &amp; holines, of wiſdome, temperance, zeale, and loue to religion, with all other good vertues: you ſhall not onely honor them heere, but alſo ſhall ſhortly meete with them in the kingdome of heauen; where chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and Parents ſhall inceſſantlie together praiſe &amp; glorifie God for euermore.</p>
            <p>You are (as it were) ſet vpon a ſtage: the eyes of manie are fixed vpon you. If you doe well, you ſhall ſatiſfie the expectation of your friends, &amp; make their hearts reioyce: if you doe ill, your enemies wil be glad, and your wel willers lament.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:12784:5"/>
In the meane ſeaſon, receiue, I beſeech you this ſmall gift, with the ſame affection wherein it is deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered by his hand, who doth daylie in his vnworthy prayers, craue earneſtlie of our mercifull Father, all good bleſsings and graces in your behalfe: &amp; (when they are according to his promiſe, performed to you) will thinke all labours &amp; indeauours, in what reſpect ſoeuer, fullie ſatisfied. And thus in haſt, I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend you to the bleſsing and tuition of the ſame Almightie God.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours as his owne in the Lord. Robert Pricke.</signed> 
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Denham</hi> in <hi>Suff.</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Septemb. 1606.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:12784:6"/>
            <head>¶ Epitaphium.</head>
            <l>MAgnorum ſeruent nomen, monumenta Virorum</l>
            <l>Marmorea: his, Pietas, marmora vera dabit.</l>
            <l>Stemmatis antiqui, faciant inſignia claros:</l>
            <l>Virtutum, his cumulus, fixa columna manet.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>Iſa. 57.1.2.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>AVreum Par amiſimus (heu) miſelli,</l>
               <l>Stemmate inſigni, pietaterara:</l>
               <l>Nec valet damnum reparare nobis,</l>
               <l>Aurea moles.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Iustus è terra perijt, nec eſt qui</l>
               <l>Curet, aufertur medio benignus:</l>
               <l>Interim, mundus ſine cura, in aurem</l>
               <l>Dormit vt ramuis.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Tollitur iustus, perijt benignus,</l>
               <l>Ne malos caſus videant propinquos,</l>
               <l>His quetem (nemine penſitante)</l>
               <l>Numine dante.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Corpus infirmum tumulus recondit;</l>
               <l>Continet fulgens animas Olympus:</l>
               <l>Gloria plenum, dies &amp; ſupremus,</l>
               <l>Iunget vtrùm<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Mente quis ſanus (ſua ſi darentur</l>
               <l>Vota) nondum ſecla beata malit,</l>
               <l>Corde ſuspirans; cito (vece clamans)</l>
               <l>Christe venito.</l>
            </lg>
            <bibl>Richardus Blackerbie.</bibl>
         </div>
         <div type="portrait">
            <pb facs="tcp:12784:6"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <p>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Richard Blackerby Dyed in the yeer <hi>1648</hi> in his 74<hi rend="sup">th</hi> year.</p>
                  <byline>F.H. Van Houe. Sculp.</byline>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:12784:7"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12784:7"/>
            <head>A Sermon preached at <hi>Denham in Suffolke.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Wiſhed, that the charge of prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching at this preſent, had bene laid vpon the ſholders of another more fit and able for the purpoſe then I am: but ſeeing the dutie doth fall vpon mee ſo neceſſarilie, that I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not put it from mee, either with honeſtie, or with a good conſcience; I muſt needes make triall by the aſsiſtance of God, what I am able to performe.</p>
            <p>Wherein, becauſe I meane, not ſo much to applie my ſelfe to the dead, as to the inſtruction and edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the liuing: I haue therefore choſen a Text, fit as I hope, for the preſent purpoſe &amp; occaſion out of the laſt chapt. of <hi>Eccleſiaſtes,</hi> 7. <hi>verſ.</hi> in theſe words.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And duſt returne to the earth as it was, and the ſpirit returne to GOD that gaue it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The principall grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d or ſcope of the whole book of Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtes, is that all things in this world are exceeding vaine.</note>The chiefe and principall point or ground of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, whereabout <hi>Salomon</hi> (the pen-man of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Ghoſt) is principallie occupyed in this booke, is brieflie propounded and ſet downe in the 2. verſ. of the 1. chapt. and that in this manner; <hi>Vanitie of vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,
<pb facs="tcp:12784:8"/>ſaith the Preacher, vanitie of vanities, all is vanitie.</hi> Whereby is ſignified, that neither true comfort, nor aſſured happineſſe doth conſiſt in anie creature vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſunne:<note place="margin">The meaning of the ſame do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, in the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall ſeope of it.</note> and all to the end that the holie Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, or rather the Spirit of God, might call mens mindes backe from too much ſtudie and delight in earthly &amp; worldly things,<note place="margin">The generall ende or vſe of the doctrine.</note> vnto the knowledge and feare of God; wherein onelie true comforte and fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitie are to be found. And for this purpoſe, he tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth his eyes round about the huge frame of this world,<note place="margin">The reaſons of it are mame.</note> &amp; by a diuine ſpirit, doth ſearch into the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, properties, effects, and euents, with the mutable eſtate of all things contained therein: from all which he gathereth ſundry &amp; manifold arguments, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he doth often proue and conclude the ſame pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition: namelie, that all things vnder the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe of heauen are nothing elſe but <hi>vanitie and vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of minde.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The laſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of all (and the ſame a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſpeciall one) is conteined in the preſent text taken from the conſideration of mans mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talitie.</note>After all which arguments, followeth this argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which I haue read, <hi>And duſt returne, &amp;c.</hi> taken from the death and diſſolution of man. The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why this argument, beeing ſo ſtrong and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſiue, is put in the laſt place; is not ſo much in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the order and degrees of mans life younger or oulder, whereof he treated a little before: not yet to proue that both man himſelfe, &amp; all things wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he is Lord and poſſeſſor,<note place="margin">The vſe which is to be made fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſame laſt reaſon: name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, that wee be carefull to ſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d our life in well dooing.</note> are fraile and tranſitorie: but for another more weightie and principall ende; namelie, to premoniſh all men to giue themſelues in their life time to well dooing, ſeeing that after this
<pb facs="tcp:12784:8"/>life is finiſhed, a man can performe nothing, either for his owne comforte, or for the benefite of other. Which is a moſt infallible truth,<note place="margin">The reaſon why ſuch vſe is to be made.</note> as is cleare and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, both by naturall reaſon &amp; experience: as alſo by the light of the word of God, which is the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall iudge and determiner of all things.<note place="margin">The firſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is from ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience and the light of nature.</note> And for the firſt; in death we all know that the inſtruments and faculties of the bodie, cunning, and skill, matter and opportunitie, doe all periſh together. Wherevp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon it followeth, that all actions and duties either acceptable to God, or profitable to man, doe vtterly ceaſe, and haue an ende.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The ſecond reaſon is taken from the word of God.</note>But for a ſecond more cleare &amp; certaine proofe: the Prophet <hi>Dauid Pſalm. 6. verſ. 5.</hi> ſaith: <hi>In death and the graue is no remembrance of God.</hi> That worthie King <hi>Ezechias,</hi> pleading with God,<note place="margin">Pſal. 6. verſ. 5.</note> for longer con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of life, vttereth theſe words:<note place="margin">Eſa 38.18.</note> 
               <hi>The graue can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not confeſſe thee, death cannot praiſe thee, they that goe down into the pit, cannot hope for thy truth, but the liuing, the liuing, hee ſhall confeſſe thee, as I doe this day.</hi> To this purpoſe <hi>Iob</hi> affirmeth,<note place="margin">Iob. 3.17.18.</note> that <hi>In the grane all ſortes doe rest and ceaſe from their labour, and duties wherein the liuing are exerciſed and toyled.</hi> We will therefore con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude with the 9. <hi>Chapter</hi> and 10. <hi>verſ.</hi> of this booke,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 9.10.</note> where the Prophet exhorteth all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in theſe words. <hi>All that thine band ſhall finde to doe, doe it with all thy po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, for there is neither worke, nor inuention, nor know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, nor wiſedome, in the graue, whether thou goeſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Exhortatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s are often ſet down in the word of God to ſtirre vs vp to make the vſe aboue mentioned fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our mortalitie. Ioh. 12.35.</note>In regard hereof, the holie Ghoſt in ſundry pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces doeth exhort vs, that wee ſhould in our life time
<pb facs="tcp:12784:9"/>when fit occaſion is offered, performe all good du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties which are commanded in the word of God. As for example, our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, ſaith vnto the people: <hi>Iohn. 12.35. ver. Whileſt it is light, take the opportunitie offered: becauſe when the night commeth, no man can worke.</hi> The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> in the 6.<note place="margin">2. Cor. 6.2.</note> 
               <hi>Chap.</hi> of the 2. to the <hi>Corinthians, 2. ver.</hi> ſaith: <hi>Behold now the accepted time, beholde now the day of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation.</hi> But yet more plainlie, the ſame Apoſtle ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horteth: <hi>while wee haue time, let vs doe good to all:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Galat. 6.10.</note> that is, while we haue time &amp; opportunitie (which onely conſiſteth and remaineth in this life) let vs performe duties: for when opportunitie is once gone &amp; paſt, it can no more be called againe, then the winde or lightening, when they are paſſed from one parte of the heauen to the other.</p>
            <p>So that it appeareth by all theſe teſtimonies, that it is the will of God, that whileſt men liue; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their life is expired by death: they ſhould bend the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues with a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ll their ſtrength, while time is graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to them) to omit no Chriſtian dutie which they owe vnto Almightie God, and vnto their brethren. Wherevnto, becauſe wee are negligent &amp; vntoward (as vnto all other duties and courſes which the Lord in his ſingular wiſedome hath appointed) therefore it is good to conſider certaine reaſons,<note place="margin">Other reaſons to the ſame ende.</note> whereby wee may be perſwaded and forced therevnto.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. From the example of the bruite crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures which ale diligent in their kinde.</note>And firſt of all, wee will beginne with brutiſh &amp; vnreaſonable creatures (as the <hi>Piſmire,</hi> the <hi>Storke,</hi> the <hi>Crane,</hi> and the <hi>Swallowe</hi>) whoſe nature and propertie
<pb facs="tcp:12784:9"/>is, as the Scripture reporteth, to diſcerne the fit ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to prouide for their owne commoditie and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite; from thoſe times wherein they cannot pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide: and therefore take the opportunitie of the firſt, before the latter commeth. And for proofe hereof, <hi>Pro. 6. Chapt. 8. verſ.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 6.8.</note> the holie Ghoſt ſpeaking of the Piſmire, ſaith, that ſhee hauing <hi>no guide, gouernour, nor ruler, prepareth her meate in ſommer, and gathereth her foode in harueſt.</hi> And the Prophet <hi>Ieremy 8. Chap. 7. verſ.</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 8 7.</note> 
               <hi>Euen the Storke in the aire knoweth her ap pointed times, &amp; the Turtle, &amp; the Crane, &amp; the Swallow obſerue the time of their comming.</hi> And to thoſe are all men ſent, to learne this leſſon: that fit opportunitie is to be taken, when it is offered; leaſt it be afterward denyed.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The 2. reaſon from the dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of men in their world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affaites.</note>But if they be aſhamed to learne of ſuch vile and baſe Schoole maſters (as indeed they haue cauſe to be aſhamed; then let them learne of Mariners, huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band-men, and men of all trades: who (leſt they ſhould be preuented) doe take fit occaſion and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunitie, to performe all actions, both by ſea and by land; which may make for their worſdly gaine and benefite. Much more then, ſhould chriſtians do the ſame, for the obteining of heauenly and diuine things.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The 3. reaſon is the ſingular fruit of a good life, which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth after death.</note>Beſides this, it is moſt certaine, that as men haue liued, ſo ſhall they die. If they haue done no good, nor brought forth chriſtian fruites in their life time: death ſhall come vpon them ſodenlie in that eſtate,<note place="margin">The 4. is the moſt wofull euent that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lovveth vpon a vvicked life.</note> and as a mightie and fearefull axe or inſtrument of
<pb facs="tcp:12784:10"/>the wrath of God ſhall cut them downe as fruitleſſe trees. And all to the end, that they may be caſt into vnquenchable fire: where is no place of doing, but of ſuffering importable torments; except to weepe, howle, and gnaſh the teeth, be dooing. A matter plaine and cleare in the rich glotton. <hi>Luk.</hi> 16. Where it is euident, that after hee had ſpent his time not in wel-doing, but in pride, exceſſe and pampering his bellie; ſodenlie he died, and was caſt into the place of torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, wher he could neither prouide for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and his owne deliuerance, nor for the benefite of his friends here vpon earth: but deſireth water to coole his tongue, and relateth in what extreame mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie he was continuallie vexed and tormented.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The 5. reaſon is the comfort of a godly life, euen here in this life.</note>There is no greater comfort vnder heauen, nor ſecuritie in al deſperate temptations of Sathan; then the conſcience of a life well led: as may appeare in the example of <hi>Iob,</hi> in the whole 31. <hi>Chap.</hi> Wherein it is euident, that he armeth himſelfe againſt Sathan, and all inſtruments which laboured to bring him to deſpaire; with no argument ſo much, as by calling to minde, how religiouſlie, and iuſtly, he had beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued himſelfe in the former courſe of his life; and hereby carried awaie a moſt renowned victorie.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The 6. reaſon is the diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in time of ſicknes, ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally at the hour of death, for neglect of lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding a godly life.</note>Furthermore, manie in ſicknes and great extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie (ſpeciallie at the houre of death) are troubled, and doe lament; for that they haue ſuffered the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer parte of their life, to paſſe a way without doe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any good duties, either toward God or their neighbour: but all in vaine. For oftentimes, the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb facs="tcp:12784:10"/>beeing paſt, and death oppreſſing them; their breath is ſhut vp in horrible deſpaire: whereupon inſueth eternall miſerie and deſtruction.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The doctrine co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluded vvith an earneſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation. <hi>Fronte capil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lata, pòſt eſt occaſio calua.</hi>
               </note>Let all perſons therefore, olde and young, men and women, of what eſtate, degree, &amp; qualitie what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer; lay holde vpon fitte time and oecaſion: re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring what the verie heathe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue ſayd, that oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion weares a buſhe before, but is balde behinde; ſo that beeing gone, it cannot be layd hold one af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward.</p>
            <p>Oh that chriſtians had wiſedome to conſider the exceeding goodnes of God, who, wher as he might haue cut of their life, ſo ſoon as they were borne; he graunteth them longer time; and fit opportunitie, to prepare themſelues for the obteining of euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life and happines. Which metcie of God, if they lightlie paſſe ouer: they ſhew themſelues moſt vnthankeful to God, and enemies vnto their owne ſoules.</p>
            <p>And thus much for the reaſon, why the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the death and diſſolution of man followeth in the laſt place: and now,<note place="margin">The text diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into tvvo parts.</note> let vs come to the <hi>Text</hi> it ſelfe, which conteineth two parts.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>A deſcription of death.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The 2. is the eſtate of the two generall and principall parts after death.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The firſt part of the text, vvhat death is.</note>Death then is nothing els, but a ſeparation of the ſoule and bodie a ſunder: or, a ſeuering and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorce of the ſoule and bodie. This deſcription is not expreſſed plainlie, and in ſo manie wordes: but it is
<pb facs="tcp:12784:11"/>neceſſarilie concluded from the <hi>Text.</hi> For if death do ſeparate the ſoule and bodie, as farre one from the other, as the heauens are diſtant from the earth: the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth it follow neceſſarilie, that death is a ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſoule and bodie. Which is alſo manifeſt, by diuers phraſes &amp; formes of ſpeach in holie Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: by which we may (by the way) clearely ſee, that death is not a ſmall or light puniſhment of ſin;<note place="margin">Death a great puniſhment of ſinne.</note> but great, heauie, and terrible. For is not that a great and mightie Tyrant, that doth rend a ſunder things that are knit, &amp; ioyned together, with ſo ſtrong and wonderfull a band, as is the bodie with the ſoule? And is not that a heauie &amp; fearefull thing, that doth part two deare friends one from an other, who ſhuld haue liued in an eternall vnion of ioy and happines, had not ſinne bene?<note place="margin">Death iuſtly terrible to all fleſh.</note> In regard whereof, it is no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, if all fleſh (euen the beſt of Gods children) doe tremble, and are aſtoniſhed at the remembrance of death,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.</note> as being a terrible enemie and a very cruell Tyrant.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Death com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to all men: and the reaſon vvhy. 1. For all haue ſinned.</note>But whatſoeuer death be, it is certainely a ſtate and condition common to all the poſteritie and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration of <hi>Adam.</hi> All men muſt die, and none can auoyd the ſtroke of death. For if death be the fruite or effect of ſinne (as it is moſt certaine, as appeareth <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.) then, ſeeing all men haue ſinned, partly in <hi>Adam,</hi> partly in themſelues: it followeth of neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, that death raigneth, and hath dominion ouer all mankinde. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.12. Which thing may yet be proued, and made more cleare. Firſt of all from the Scriptures.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:12784:11"/>
Secondly, by continuall experience.</p>
            <p>From the Scriptures, two waies.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. It is Gods decree and iuſt ſentence.</note>Firſt, by the ſentence of God pronounced vpon all mankinde.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">3. God is faith full in execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence as expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth.</note>Againe, by the execution of that dreadfull ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence.</p>
            <p>For proofe of the firſt: It appeareth, that the Lord gaue charge to <hi>Adam</hi> in his innocencie, that hee ſhould not eat of the tree of the knowledge of good and euil: threatning, that if hee did eate,<note place="margin">The proofe and amplifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the firſt and ſecond reaſon.</note> or taſte thereof, he ſhould die the death. But <hi>Adam</hi> did eate of the tree forbidden, and ſo treſpaſſed againſt the Commandement: and therefore God foorth with gaue ſentence in theſe words; <hi>Earth thou art, and to earth thou ſhalt returne.</hi> That is, I haue decreed &amp; ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed as a puniſhment for thy ſinne; that both thy ſelfe and all thy poſteritie conteined in thy loynes, ſhall not only be ſubiect to eternall miſery, but alſo ſhall ſuffer a corporal or natural death. Wherevpon it followeth, that death is moſt certaine and ineui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table. For why? all men muſt of neceſſitie taſte of death: it cannot be ſhunned or auoided. And as the ſentence it ſelfe is certaine, and vnrepealeable, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from the mouth of him that is truth it ſelfe, and vnchangeable: ſo the execution of that ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, is ſo certaine and infallible, that no meanes or prerogatiue can reſiſt, or preuaile againſt it.<note place="margin">The proofe and amplifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the third reaſon.</note> Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther length of dayes, nor wiſdome, nor riches, nor honour, nor ſtrength: no, not that excellent gift of regeneration. The auncient Fathers,<note place="margin">The Patriarks though they liued long, yet are long ſince dead. Salomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thogh moſt wiſe: yet is dead. Samſon, thogh moſt ſtrong, yet he is dead. Dauid, Moſes, all the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, though moſt holy in their times, are dead.</note> and Patriarkes
<pb facs="tcp:12784:12"/>before the flood, liued verie long, ſome 700. ſome 800. ſome 900. yeares: yet it is ſaid of euery one, hee died and was gathered to his Fathers. <hi>Salomon</hi> was wiſe, and excelled all Kings before him, and ſince his time, in riches &amp; glory. <hi>Sampſon</hi> was endued with extraordinary ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth. <hi>Dauid</hi> was a man after Gods owne heart. <hi>Moſes</hi> ſawe God face to face. The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets were endued with a great meaſure of ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification: yet the Prophet <hi>Zachary</hi> ioynes them all together in one ſtate of mortalitie, in the firſt Chap. verſe 5. <hi>Your fathers where are they? and doe the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets liue for euer?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zach.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.5.</note> Vpon this ground, the Holy Ghoſt in diuers places of the Scripture, affirmeth that man borne of a woman is of ſhort continuance, and full of trouble: that he ſhooteth forth as a flower, and vaniſheth alſo as a ſhadow, and continueth not. That a man can by no meanes redeeme his brother, that he may liue ſtill and not ſee the graue. Yea, as a thing commonly knowne, death (in a prouerbiall manner) is called the way of all fleſh. So loude cryeth the holy Scripture, that all men are ſubiect to death. But if this voyce were ſilent, yet expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience doth ſpeake out the matter ſo plainly, that the greateſt dullard and rude perſon may vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand. For to what ende ſerue ſo many Funeralls of all ſorts,<note place="margin">All ſorts of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> die euery day.</note> olde, young, rich, poore, noble, and baſe? To what ende, ſo many Graues and Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, in the places of buriall? ſo many drie bones caſt out of the Graues? but to ſet forth viſiblie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our eyes, the mortall eſtate of mankinde.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:12784:12"/>
Whereby is diſcouered, and laide open, the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame blindnes and dulneſſe of the moſt part. For although they be conuinced both by the teſtimony of God and nature, that all men muſt die: yet reape they little or no benefite by it.<note place="margin">The greater &amp; more groſſe is the ſinne of all that profit not by the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of death, in the care of a god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly life.</note> For ſome lye roc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ſo faſt a ſleepe in ſecuritie, and in the pleaſures of this worlde, that they thinke no more of death, then the bruite beaſt that is without vnderſtanding. Other can diſcourſe finely of death, to make ſhew of their eloquence and learning: and yet will not by ſerious meditation, applie the remembrance of death to their hearts. Finally, verie many doe quake and tremble at death, who yet for all that, vſe no meanes that they may die well.</p>
            <p>I will not at this time, recite the cauſes and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons hereof, which are diuers and manifold: only I may conclude, that all theſe ſorts are in a miſerable caſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The duties of all Chriſtians in reſpect of their mortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</note>For auoyding whereof, we muſt take a cleane contrary courſe; which ſtandeth herein, that we do ſeriouſly meditate of death, and as it were continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſet it before our eyes: and that not for diſcourſe, or ſpeculation; but for more weigntie &amp; profitable endes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. We are to vvithdravv our hearts from all inordinat loue of this vvorld, and the tranſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory thinges thereof.</note>And firſt of all, to the end we may withdraw and weane our hearts from too much delight in this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall life; and in the things that belong therevnto. And there is great reaſon thereof. For ſeeing that both life, and the things of this world, are fraile, tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitorie, and vncertaine: true felicitie cannot conſiſt
<pb facs="tcp:12784:13"/>in them. How much better then were it for men, by the conſideration hereof, to ſet their affections, not on things belowe, but vpon things that are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue: and to laie vp their treaſure in heauen, where neither ruſt, nor moath can conſume, nor theeues breake through and ſteale?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. We are to humble our ſelues vnder the mightie hand of God, and his feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſentence of death a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſinne.</note>The ſecond ende, is to beate downe the pride and inſolencie of men, whereby they are puffed vp as though they were Gods immortall heere vpon earth. From which conceipt (as from a curſed ſinke) doe flowe blaſphemies againſt God; out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rages, doe flowe blaſphemies againſt God; out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rages, iniuries, and violences againſt men; yea, a thouſand miſchiefes and abhominations; whereat the Sunne in heauen, doth as it were ſtand ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed. For which cauſe, the hand of the Lord doth ſtrike the world with infinite calamities and iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">3. We are to lead our liues in godlines, &amp; vſe all good meanes there. of, that we may die with comfort.</note>The laſt and ſpeciall ende, is, that men may be induced to apply their hearts vnto wiſedome; that is, that by diligent and carefull vſing the holie and good meanes, which God hath ſet vp in the church (as the miniſtery of the word and Sacraments, &amp;c.) they may thereby attaine ſuch a meaſure of faith, repentance, and holines, that they may not trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble at the terrible face of death: but (knowing, and beeing perſwaded that his ſting is pulled out, and his weapons broken by the vertue of the death of our Lorde and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt) they may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaine him as a friende, and yeeld to him as to a Porter or Harbinger, appointed by GOD, to
<pb facs="tcp:12784:13"/>make a waye for all the faithfull, vnto the place of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting happineſſe.</p>
            <p>Againe, that they may not die in trouble, or vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of conſcience: but in ſuch a ſweete tranquilli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of minde, that they may with <hi>Simeon</hi> ſay: <hi>Lorde now letteſt thou thy ſeruant depart in peace.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luc. 2.29.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Finallie, that they may not ſee the mouth of hell gaping to deuoure and ſwallow them vp: but by the eies of faith, behold with <hi>Stephen,</hi> the heauens open, and the Lord Ieſus Chriſt ſtanding at the right hand of God his Father, readie to receiue their ſoules.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">It is a ſpeciall grace of God, which teacheth men to make the former good vſes fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our mortalitie.</note>We ſee here, the ſingular fruits that growe from the ſeriours meditation of death, and the due prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration for it. Which yet is not a worke of nature, but proceedeth from God and his holie ſpirit: without whoſe vertue and operation, nothing (be it neuer ſo cleare, neuer ſo great and forcible) can work effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allie in the hearts ſo great and forcible) can work effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allie in the hearts of men. Which thing was ſo well knowne to <hi>Moſes,</hi> that in the 90. <hi>Pſal.</hi> he crieth out,<note place="margin">And therefore wee ought to praye earneſtly to God for ſo ſpeciall a grace Pſal. 90.12.</note> 
               <hi>Teach vs O Lorde ſo to nomber our dayes, that we may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie our hearts vnto wiſedome.</hi> Which example, euery one of vs are to follow; not onely becauſe it is recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in Scripture: but becauſe that ſodaine and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prouided for death, doth bring ſo manie euills with it: to wit, ſuch feare and trembling, ſuch horror, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh, &amp; deſpaire: that manie wiſh at the firſt aſſault thereof, that they had neuer beene borne, nor ſeene the light of the ſunne: as we haue had too manie ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples in theſe our dayes.</p>
            <p>Well therefore did theſe two worſhipfull per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,
<pb facs="tcp:12784:14"/>who long before their death and diſſolution,<note place="margin">The godlie couple late de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted, were notable exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples right wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie our imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion herein.</note>) had not onely the name of death, and of the ende of this life, often in their mouthes: but by all good meanes fitted themſelues for the comming of the Lord. Which manie neglecting, death commeth ſodenlie vppon them, before they can prepare oyle for their lamps: and ſo are they ſhut out of the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacles of eternall life &amp; happines; and caſt down into an eſtate moſt miſerable, and to be trembed at of all Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>And thus much of death, with the certaintie and vniuerſalitie thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The ſecond part of the Text.</note>Now let vs come to the ſecond pointe of the <hi>Text:</hi> namely, of the eſtate of the generall and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall parts of man, after death.</p>
            <p>The parts are two,<note place="margin">The eſtate of man after death both in bodie and ſoule.</note>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The Soule, and</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The Bodie.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Of which the holie Ghoſt ſpeaketh ſeuerallie, and diſtinctlie.</p>
            <p>But becauſe the bodie is more viſible, and beſt knowne;<note place="margin">The eſtate of the bodie. The originall of the bodie is from the earth. And this conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth very aptlie to the illuſtration folowing after, both in, and by death. Gen. 2.7.</note> hee beginneth firſt with that: which he deſcribeth two wayes. Firſt, in it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Secondlie, by relation: that is, by reference to the place to which it belongeth, or wherevnto it is to be committed.</p>
            <p>In it ſelfe, by this word duſt; in the originall <hi>[He gnaphar]</hi> noting out the matter whereof the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy is made, agreeable with the hyſtorie of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.7. in theſe words. <hi>The Lord alſo made man
<pb facs="tcp:12784:14"/>of the dust of the earth:</hi> where the ſelfe ſame Hebrew word is vſed.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The reaſon why it pleaſed God to make the bodie of man of the earth.</note>The reaſon why God mad the bodie of man of ſuch baſe matter, &amp; doth ſo often mention it in holie Scripture; was (no doubt) to humble man, and to repreſſe that inſolencie wherewith hee might eaſilie haue bene puffed vp, in regard of his excellent eſtate in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pariſon of other creatures: if he had not ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his eyes, both his originall, &amp; alſo what manner of manſion place, or dwelling that is,<note place="margin">It is a moſt ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuallmeanes to humbleman</note> wherein th ſoule is ſtill to be lodged. For theſe are verie forcible <hi>Arguments,</hi> to abaſe and caſt downe the loftie hearts of all men, which otherwiſe might (as was ſaid) haue bene more eaſilie puffed vp. As for example, if his bodie had proceeded fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the glorious matter of the ſunne, and the heauens aboue,<note place="margin">Iob. 37.18.</note> which <hi>Iob</hi> compareth to moulten glaſſe for the puritie and brightnes: and ſo conſequentlie his ſoule had dwelt in a ſtately pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, ſutable to the excellent nature thereof: he had had (as might haue ſeemed,) ſome greater occaſion to lifte vp himſelfe aboue other creatures. But now when as earth and duſt is his mother, which he daily treadeth vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; dwelleth in,<note place="margin">Iob. 4.19.</note> as (<hi>Iob</hi> ſaith) in an houſe of Clay: there is ſmall cauſe why he ſhuld conceiue highlie of himſelfe. If a man which comes of a No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble parentage, &amp; dwells in a houſe agreeable to his eſtate: it is (as wee would thinke) ſome peece of an excuſe, though hee ſhould be ſomething high min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. But if a poore creature, who is deſcended of baſe parentage, and withall dwelleth and lodgeth in
<pb facs="tcp:12784:15"/>a poore cottage built and framed of mudde &amp; clay, ſhould neuertheleſſe hautilie exalte himſelfe aboue others:<note place="margin">The pride of man is the more mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous and finnefull.</note> it would iuſtly be counted ſo much the more monſtrous, and intollerable pride. How monſtrous then and abſurd is the pride of man: who being but a wretched worme and dirt it ſelfe, doth yet exalte himſelfe, not only aboue all other creatures, but eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againſt the mightie Lord his Creator, whoſe ſeate is the glorious pallace of the whole heauens? From whence, we may gather a double vſe. And firſt of all, that whenſoeuer wee feele our ſelues conceited with anie ſpeciall gift or qualitie, which wee lifte vp and ſpread abroad as peacocks feathers: that we pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently looke vpon our vile and fraile bodies, as vpon black feete, which wil eaſilie cauſe our glorious taile to ſincke and fall downe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, hereby we may ſee the extream madnes, and more then <hi>diuelliſh &amp; Luciferian pride of Atheiſts,</hi> and profane worldlings:<note place="margin">The pride of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is the more fooliſh, vaine, and pernicious to himſelfe.</note> who doe ſo ſwell, and are puffed vp with ſuch a vaine conceite of their owne excellencie, that they doe not onely contemne God their Lord and Creator; but as Giants doe make o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen warre againſt him. Which perſons, (ſeeing that the ſight of their owne baſeneſſe will not humble them) aſſuredlie, the hand of God (with ſome feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full thunderbolt of his wrath) wil one day ſo repreſſe them and cruſh them: that they ſhalbe inforced to confeſſe (will they, nill they) their baſe eſtate &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, in compariſon of their Lords and Creator. Which they may ſee by an example verified in <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buchadnezzar,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Examples of</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:12784:15"/>who becauſe hee would not acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge God; and ſtoope to him as to his Superiour:<note place="margin">Gods iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes againſt proud perſons.</note> was by the iuſt iudgement of his mighty Lorde and Soueraigne, ſtript &amp; ſpoiled of his kingdom,<note place="margin">Dan. 4.30.</note> &amp; liued the ſpace of 7. years in the ſtate of a bruit beaſt that ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth graſſe, till he did acknowledge himſelfe a mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall man.<note place="margin">2. Chro. 32.10.</note> They may ſee it likewiſe in <hi>Sancherib</hi> the great King of <hi>Aſſyria,</hi> who was lifted vp ſo high in the pride of his heart, that hee durſt blaſpheme the Eternall. But what got he thereby?<note place="margin">21.</note> The Lord made hauock of his huge Armie: put a hooke in his noſe: cauſed him to returne home againe with ſhame and confuſion: &amp; anone after, ſtirred vp his two ſonnes, who moſt vnnaturallie ſlew him in the temple of his falſe Gods. What ſhall I ſpeake of <hi>Herod</hi> the King,<note place="margin">Act. 12. vlt.</note> 
               <hi>Act. 12.</hi> who could finde in his heart to arrogate to himſelfe the worſhip and honour due vnto God, which was giuen vnto him by his wicked flatterers? but the Lord by his Angell ſtroke him with a lowſie and loath-full diſeaſe,<note place="margin">A zealous and godlie admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition to all, that they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of pride.</note> whereof hee miſerablie peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed. Wherefore Oh earth, earth, earth, humble thy ſelfe, and ſtoope downe before him, whoſe glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Maieſtie, not onely the Elect Angels, but alſo the diuels adore and tremble at. And alwayes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member thou, that God, of all other ſinnes cannot abide the pride and loftineſſe of Man:<note place="margin">It is the vſuall way &amp; dealing of God to take vengeance vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> proud perſons. 1. Pet. 5.5. Luc. 2.52.53.</note> as may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by ſundrie ſpeeches, in diuers places of the holie Scripture, which teſtifie that <hi>God reſiſteth the proude:</hi> that, <hi>Hee beholdeth the proude a farre off:</hi> that, <hi>Hee filleth the hungrie with good things, and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth
<pb facs="tcp:12784:16"/>the rich emptie away,</hi> and ſuch like. Which all doe ſerue to bring all men to true humilitie: which is a ſweete and amiable vertue, opening a way for all excellent graces of God into the ſoule of a man that is trulie humbled.</p>
            <p>But this which wee haue ſpoken hetherto of the matter whereof the bodie is made, was the eſtate of man before ſinne, &amp; ſhould haue continued though man had not trangreſſed. That is, he ſhould haue conſiſted of an earthly body &amp; a ſpiritual foule.</p>
            <p>Nowe that which followeth in the next wordes of our Text, came in by ſinne: and therefore is farre worſe, and more miſerable; in theſe wordes, <hi>returne to the earth as it was.</hi> For thereby is ſignified, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie the ſimple buriall of the dead bodie:<note place="margin">The eſtate of mans earthly bodie in, and after death. It may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered in three degrees. 1. It is voyd of ſenſe &amp; motion 2. It is vtterlie defaced. 3. It putrifieth and turneth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to baſe earth.</note> but alſo the eſtate thereof after it is buried, and layd in the earth. Which conſiſteth of diuers effects.</p>
            <p>For firſt of all, the bodie lyeth in the graue ſenſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, and without motion euen as a blocke or ſtone.</p>
            <p>Againe, the maieſtie and beautie of the face and whole bodie departeth: and a pale, deformed, and vglie forme ſucceedes.</p>
            <p>Thirdlie, the bodie putrifieth and rotteth: and from thence proceedes a moſt horrible and ſtinking ſauour, and in the ende is wholie turned into duſt. Which is the eſtate of all men (yea, euen of <hi>Dauid</hi> himſelfe,) the bodie of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt onely excepted, which by a ſpeciall prerogatiue, ſawe no corruption at all.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The vſes to be made of the former conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the bodies eſtate in &amp; by death.</note>Which beeing ſo: what doe young gallantes meane (both men &amp; women,) ſo to paint their faces,
<pb facs="tcp:12784:16"/>and frownce their haire as they vſe to doe? ſeeing that baldnes ſhall couer their heads, and their viſages ſhall become ſo pale, and fearefull; that the ſtrongeſt hearted; yea they themſelues, if they could poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie diſcerne it; ſhould not be able to beare the view thereof: but they muſt needes quake, tremble, and abhorre themſelues. And what reaſon haue the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picures, delicates, and belly-gods of the world, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſiuelie to pamper and ſtuffe their bodies with the moſt daintie meates and drinks, ſeeing they muſt of neceſsitie rot, putrifie, and conſume to duſt &amp; aſhes?</p>
            <p>And to what purpoſe, doe a great manie carrie about them continuallie ſuch exceſſe of ſweete ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours and perfumes? for as much as their carkaſſes are within a while after, to caſt forth ſuch an horrible and contagious ſmell, as the leaſt part whereof, were able to infect a whole citie or countrie. All which expences therefore, are but ſuperfluous, vanitie and loſt labour.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Neuertheleſſe, the bodies of thoſe that haue led a godlie life ſhall not conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue alwayes in this ſenſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed eſtate.</note>But heere, ſome man may demaund, whether the bodies of the dead, ſhall alwayes remaine in this eſtate, without change and reſtitution? which if it be ſo, it ſeemeth that the ſoule is euill matched, with ſuch a bodie: &amp; that there is no difference betweene the ſtate of the bodies of bruite beaſts, and the eſtate of men, who are (by the dignitie of creation) their Lords and Superiours.</p>
            <p>The anſwere heerevnto is, that the dead bodies of men ſhall be reſtored by the laſt and finall reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. For by the vertue, power, &amp; ſpirit of our Lord
<pb facs="tcp:12784:17"/>Ieſus Chriſt; whereby his owne bodie was quicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and raiſed vp from the dead: ſhall the bodyes of all the faithfull, firſt of all bee quickened, and rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vp (their ſoules reſtored to them againe) &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withall the qualities of their bodies ſhalbee changed from their former worſe,<note place="margin">The bodies of the faithfull ſhall bee raiſed from death &amp; be made thenc forth glorious &amp; immortall.</note> to a better renewed eſtate: to wit, from mortall, to immortall: fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> corruption to incorruption: from earthly, to heauenly: fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> weake, to ſtrong, from baſe to glorious. For why? their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies ſhalbe conformed like to the glorious bodie of of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt: ſo that the iuſt ſhall ſhine as the ſunne in the kingdome of their Father. All which is very largely handled,<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 4. 1. Cor. 15. Phil. 3.21. Mat. 13.43.</note> and ſet forth, 1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.21. <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.43. Wherein it appeareth, that whatſoeuer wound, or loſſe, the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die receiueth by death: the ſame is healed, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored againe, by the reſurrection of the dead. And therefore, as the Scripture doth often make men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the reſurrection of the deade, and all the faithfull doe earneſtlie wiſh and longe after it:<note place="margin">Three vſes to be made from the doctrine of the reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; our beliefe in that reſpect.</note> ſo I beſeech you let our meditations, and thoughts, be continually occupied about it. For why? the true knowledge and remembrance of it, doth ſerue for many good and comfortable vſes.<note place="margin">1. we are more willing to die our ſelues whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the time ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt of all, it cauſeth a man willingly to put off his earthly Tabernacle, ſeeing hee ſhall reſume, and be clad with another from heauen, farre more excellent and glorious.<note place="margin">2. we haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in the death &amp; burial of our godly friends who dy before vs.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Again, it miniſtreth comfort to them that beſtow and lay vp the dead bodies of their friends, in the
<pb facs="tcp:12784:17"/>graues: for why? they know they doe not yeeld, or deliuer them vp to deſtruction; but lay them vp, as it were in ſoft beds: to the end, that they may ſleepe quietly, till they be awaked by the ſound of the laſt Trumpet.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">3 It ſtirreth vs vp to the care of a godly life that ſo we may haue comfort in death.</note>Finally, if men thinke earneſtly of the laſt reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection: it cannot but ſtir them vp, ſo to liue and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues in this life: that they may haue a ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and bleſſed reſurrection. For whie? all ſhall not be raiſed vp to glorie and happines; but many to ſhame and eternal confuſion, as appeareth.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.29. <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.2</note>5. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 29 12. <hi>Dan.</hi> 2. All which, being true and vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: let vs hold and maintaine the true doctrine of the reſurrection,<note place="margin">The former doctrine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded with a louing &amp; mild exhortation.</note> and continuallie ſet it before our eies, to the end that wee may thereby ſtirre vp our ſelues to walke on and continue in ſuch a holy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation; that at the ſecond co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming of Ieſus Chriſt the Lord of the reſurrection, wee may not deſire the mountains &amp; hills to fall vpon vs:<note place="margin">The eſtate of the ſoule after the death of the bodie.</note> but rather lift vp our heads, and looke for the full accompliſhment of our redemption. Thus much of the ſtate of the bodie after death.<note place="margin">It returneth to God.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Now followeth likewiſe, the eſtate of the ſoule after death, in theſe wordes.<note place="margin">The ſoule of man is immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as it is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by many reaſons. And all theſe make way verie profitably to the deſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the eſtate of the ſoule fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing after.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſpirit returneth to him that gaue it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From whence, wee firſt obſerue, that the ſoule of man is not the naturall ſpirits of the bodie, nor fire and heate: nor breath &amp; vapor, nor any accide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tal qualitie, which periſheth with death, as wee ſee in bruite beaſtes: but a ſpirituall &amp; immortal ſubſtance,
<pb facs="tcp:12784:18"/>which remaineth after death.<note place="margin">1 Becauſe it va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth not, but goeth to God.</note> For how can a vapor or rather that which is nothing, remoue from earth to heauen? Yea, for further confirmation; when our Sauiour ſaith to the repentant Thiefe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 23.43.</note> 
               <hi>This day ſhalt thou be with me in Paradiſe:</hi> that is, in euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting ioy &amp; happines: he could not poſſiblie meane the bodie; for that was taken downe from the gib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet and laid in the earth: but he muſt needes meane the ſoule diuorced and ſeuered from the bodie.<note place="margin">2. Becauſe the ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of God deſier to haue their Soules looſened from the bodie.</note>
            </p>
            <p>In like manner, the Apoſtle <hi>Paule</hi> deſired to bee diſſolued and to be with Chriſt: he knew very well that his body ſhould returne anone after, to the duſt and therefore deſireth to be preſent with Chriſt not in bodie but in ſoule.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">3 Becauſe they doe with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort commend them to God when they dy Pſal. 31.5. Luke. 23.46. Act. 7.59</note>Furthermore, with what conſcience, and truth could the holy ſeruants of God, ſay, <hi>Father into thine hand I commend my ſpirit:</hi> if the ſoule did immediatly after death, periſh and vaniſh into the aire?</p>
            <p>Laſtly, how is it poſſible, that empty aire, and a thing without eſſence, ſhould be endued with ſuch affections,<note place="margin">4 Becauſe they are indued with pure and earneſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections after that they are ſundred from the bodie.</note> as that in heauen and eternall glory, they ſhould wiſh &amp; deſire the accompliſhment, &amp; perfect felicity of all the elect: as the Euangeliſt doth attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to the ſoules of the ſeruants of God, which are departed in the faith of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">5 The immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talitie of the ſoule hath ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny famous te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies from many of the heathen.</note>Wherevpon it followeth, that the ſoule of man is an immortall ſubſtance. Which was a thing well known alſo to the heathen, by the light of nature: whoſe iudgment and ſentences, it weare an eaſie matter here to recite: but that the holy Scriptures
<pb facs="tcp:12784:18"/>are ſo cleare, and ſufficient in the point (as in all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) that he which will not credit them: will not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue nor be perſwaded, though one ſhould riſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain from the dead. And yet ſome of the ſayings of heathen men, are here ſet down to the view of thoſe that haue a mind to ſee them:
<floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="sayings">
                  <body>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Firſt of</hi> Plato, <hi>of whoſe diſputation of the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalitie of the ſoule, this is the ſumme. Pſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che ara athanatos, &amp;c. The ſoule the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is immor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tal, &amp; ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not periſh, &amp;c</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Phocylides.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Pſuchaigar mimnouſi acerioi. &amp;c. The ſoules remaine in corruptible, or immortall, &amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Cyrus <hi>apud</hi> Xenopho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: <hi>in his Oration to his children a little before his death.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Plutarch <hi>citeth an O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle for this purpoſe, vttered to one</hi> Corax Naxus, <hi>in theſe words Ouc hoſioneſti tes pſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches catagnonai tha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naton. It is a wicked thing to acknowledge any death of the ſoule. See alſo the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of Tullie, in the firſt booke of his Tuſcul. queſtions.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Hetherto doe pertaine the fancies of Hell: of the Elyſian
fields, &amp;c. deſcribed in Homer &amp; Virgill.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Hether, the honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and carefull bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rials of the deade, the i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magined walking of Ghoſtes, or ſpirits after death, &amp; ſuch like.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
&amp; to make ſome vſe of them, againſt all prophane and hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> that (liuing vnder the Goſpell) go not yet ſo far in this point, as they did: nay come verie far ſhort of them, to their great ſhame. From all which reaſons it may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, that in vaine doe the <hi>Atheiſts</hi> (whereof we haue too manie examples) puffe out a little warme breath in ſcorne and deriſion, ſaying, there go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth my ſoule: he being there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in fowlie deceiued, and ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth himſelfe vtterlie impude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and ſhameleſſe. It were a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed thing for thee, oh thou <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſt,</hi> if thou wert in the eſtate of a bruit beaſt. But alas, thou art indued with an immortall ſoule, which can neuer die:
<pb facs="tcp:12784:19"/>
wherof thou art euen convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in thy ſelfe; but that the diuell hath blinded thine eyes, and ſtrongly poſſeſſed thy heart.</p>
            <p>For what is the reaſon that thou doeſt ſo tremble at death, and art ſo loth to die? Is it becauſe this life is a paradiſe, full of all pleaſure and happines to thee? that cannot be: for rather it is a Sea, fraught and toſſed vp and down, with ſuch extreame miſeries, woes and calamities, which doe oftentimes cauſe thee to grone and complaine. And therefore, the cauſe is the guilt and accuſation of an euill conſcience: from which thou doeſt conclude, that immediatly after death, thou ſhalt ſuffer euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting torments and confuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in hel fire: which doth plainely proue to thy ſhameleſſe face, that a princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall part of thee doth ſtill remaine after death: and that is thy ſoule.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The eſtate of the ſoule of man after the departure fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the bodie.</note>But to omit theſe graceles Caitifs: let vs in theſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond place, conſider what becomes of the ſoule after death. For anſwer herevnto: it doth not wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der vp and downe from place to place, nor yet remaineth in a third place, as <hi>Papiſts &amp; Pagans</hi> haue dreamed, without warrant of gods word: but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently (as our text ſaith) it returneth vnto God that gaue it,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.</note> or created it: as appeareth <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 2. which ſpeach (if it be not warily vnderſtoode) doth firſt of all ſeeme to fauour the opinion of them, that
<pb facs="tcp:12784:19"/>affirme that not one of them which God hath crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſhalbe condemned. And ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly, profane Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cures, and vngodlie perſons, will thereof conclude, that they may liue as they liſt. For howſoeuer they tumble and wallow in all manner of ſinne and abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations: yet all is verie well, For whie? as they imagine; after death, their ſoules and ſpirits ſhall enioye the preſence and glorie of God for euer and euer, inſomuch as they returne to God.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The eſtate of the ſoules of the godlie and wicked are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, yea cleane co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary: thogh the ſoules of all doe goe vnto God.</note>For preuenting, and anſwering of both which ſorts: wee are to vnderſtand, that in this place, the holie Ghoſt meaneth not, that the ſoules of all men without exception, ſhalbe ſaued; or enioy the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull preſence of God for euer: but that the ſoules of euerie one, ſhall immediately after death, appeare before God their creator &amp; Iudge; who will reward the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> according to that they haue done in the bodie, whether it be good or euill. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. For confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion wherof, it is ſaid,<note place="margin">Heb. 9.27.</note> that after death co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And the truth thereof we ſee <hi>Luc:</hi> 16. in poore <hi>Lazarus</hi> and the rich glotton.<note place="margin">Luc. 16.22.23</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The ſoules of the godlie are bleſſed &amp; hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie for euer af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this life ended.</note>So that the ſoules of them that that haue belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and obeyed the will of his heauenlie Father; doe preſentlie meete with the Lord Ieſus in Paradiſe: are gathered into the boſom of <hi>Abraham:</hi> doe enioy vnſpeakeable happines and glorie. But contrariwiſe, the ſoules of ſuch infidells, as haue contemned Chriſt and his Goſpel,<note place="margin">The ſoules of the wicked are for euer moſt accurſed and miſerable.</note> and haue ſhewed themſelues diſobedient: they doe forth with &amp; without ſtay, paſſe into a place of torments: where
<pb facs="tcp:12784:20"/>the worme neuer dieth, &amp; their fire neuer goeth out: yea, where they liue in anguiſh, paine and affliction, till the bodie (for the further increaſe of their miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie) be reſtored to the ſoule againe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The doctrine is doubled, to ſhevve the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taintie, and to cauſe the more deep impreſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers.</note>From whence it followeth, that as the eſtate of infidels is moſt curſed and fearefull: ſo is the eſtate of thoſe that die in the Lord, moſt bleſſed &amp; happie. For why? (ſaith the Spirit) <hi>they reſt from their labours, &amp; their works follow them: &amp; all teares ſhalbe wiped from their eyes,</hi> being not onely deliuered from all matter of griefe, ſorrowe, heauineſſe, and calamitie; but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo doe enioy at the right hand of God, pleaſures for euermore: to wit, they are partakers of ſuch com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, peace, and felicitie, as the eye hath not ſeene, the eare hath not heard, neither hath it entred into the heart of man.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A worthie ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplification of all the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer doctrine, from the godly couple latelie departed this life, and liuing aſſuredlie in heauen with the ſoules of the righteous for euer and euer.</note>Into the which eſtate, there is no doubt, but that theſe two right worſhipfull perſons, I meane <hi>Sir Edward Lewkenor Knight,</hi> and the vertuous Ladie <hi>Suſan</hi> his wife, (whoſe funerall this day is heere cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated and held) are, by the free mercie of God, pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced and aduanced. For why? as they liued well, ſo they dyed. In their life they loued, and ſerued God: and at the length ſlept in the Lorde. For proofe hereof, we wil not reſort to the deceitfull weights of humane reaſon, nor anie morall or ciuill Vertue, which may be found in heathens that neuer knewe God:<note place="margin">Reaſons for proofe of their bleſſed eſtate.</note> but to the golden and infallible ballance of the holie Scripture. Wherin (among other ſignes and arguments) we finde eſpeciallie two, whereby a
<pb facs="tcp:12784:20"/>true Chriſtian may be deſcryed and diſcerned:<note place="margin">1. They were called by the preaching of the Goſpel. 2. They were trulie ſanctified by the holie Spirit of God. Many reaſons alleadged to prooue their effectuall cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.</note> and that, both in life and death.</p>
            <p>The firſt, is a true and effectuall calling.</p>
            <p>The other, is true ſanctification: after which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth eternall glorification. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.</p>
            <p>That they were both effectually called, may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by diuers arguments. And firſt of all, they were inlightned and converted by the miniſterie of the Goſpell preached: which in an ordinarie time, is a ſure token of an effectuall calling.</p>
            <p>Beſides,<note place="margin">1. Reaſon. Rom. 10.15.17</note> they both imbraced Chriſt Ieſus by a liuely faith,<note place="margin">2. Reaſon.</note> in whom they found &amp; felt ſuch ſweete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes &amp; aſſurance, with peace of conſcience, and full<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of life and ſaluation: that they accompted all things in the world but droſſe, in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pariſon of him. Yea, they renounced and abhorred from their verie hearts, all meanes of ſaluation, redemption, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation with God, inuented by mans braine, and ioyned with him in the worke of iuſtification, either in parte or in whole.</p>
            <p>Againe, they loued moſt dearelie, the miniſterie of the word, and miniſters thereof, all their life after:<note place="margin">3. Reaſon.</note> by the which, as by an immortall ſeede, they knewe they were borne anewe, through the operation and working of the holie Ghoſt. And therefore pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued this holie ordinance of God, and the miniſters thereof, with no leſſe reuerence and tender affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; then naturall children doe their naturall Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, of whom they are bred and begotten.</p>
            <p>Furthermore,<note place="margin">4. Reaſon.</note> all ſuch as were begotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the ſame
<pb facs="tcp:12784:21"/>means (&amp; thereby had the image of God repaired in them) were ſo deare &amp; precious in their eyes: as that they preferred the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before all others (althogh neerely linked to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) that were not in the ſame <hi>eſtate of grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To conclude: they were not conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted with their owne calling,<note place="margin">5. Reaſon.</note> but they deſired &amp; laboured the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion of others; eſpecially of them of their own fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milie: as may appeare by their holy exhortations, &amp; carefull in couragements, and by their vertuous ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of life ſet before the eyes of all.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, by their continual praying, reading, medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting,<note place="margin">6. Reaſon.</note> and conferring of the word of God, with other holie exerciſes: wherewith the hearts of manie were exceedingly rauiſhed, &amp; the remembrance whereof (as I truſt) will neuer dye in the hearts of them that were partakers thereof, ſo long as they ſhall liue.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By all which arguments, their effectual calling is clearely proued. And if they be not ſufficient to argue &amp; prooue it, I knowe not what is.</hi> Nowe concerning their Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, another ſigne that they dyed in the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Reaſons to prooue their ſanctification.</note>
               <hi>Sanctification,</hi> is known vnto man by the <hi>outward co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation,</hi> man ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſearch or ſee no further. For <hi>that be. longeth to God the ſearcher of the heart &amp; reynes.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore what <hi>their outward conuerſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was,</hi> we wil next <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire:</hi> &amp; that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning both of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <hi>ſeuerally &amp; apart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">And firſt the vertues of the Chriſtian Lady who dyed firſt, are faithfully teſtified and rehearſed.</note>And firſt, we will begin with the Ladie, becauſe it was her lotte to departe out of this world before her husband. What her <hi>conuerſation was, it is well knowne to all:</hi> and yet it ſhall not bee amiſſe, at this preſent, more diſtinctlie to declare.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:12784:21"/>
               <note place="margin">An example worthie the i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitation of al, women: ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally of Ladies &amp; Gentle wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Read it dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly good Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewomen and weigh it through out.</note>To this purpoſe more generally, ſhe was indued with moſt of thoſe vertues, expreſſed in the Epiſtles of <hi>Paul,</hi> in the <hi>Prouer. of Salomon,</hi> and other places of holie Scripture, required in a true Chriſtian, and an holy woman. For why? although ſhe was worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullie deſcended, and indued with excellent giftes: yet ſhe walked not with hautie eies, deſpiſing and diſdaining the baſer ſorte, and ſuch as were farre her inferiours; but willingly and chearefully did ſtoope downe to them, and ſo humblie conuerſed with them, as if they had ben her equalls. Shee was temperat in her diet and apparrel, profeſſing that fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> her childhood ſhe neuer delighted in thoſe toyes,<note place="margin">An obſeruatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> moſt neceſſary for the wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this moſt vaine and new fangled age.</note> vanities and ſuperfluities of attire, wherewith many women, (otherwiſe vertuous and truly religious) are. She was louing, and tender to her children: but yet with ſingular diſcretion. Shee loued her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, and was dutifull to him, ſhining before his eies (as a ſtarre) in chaſtitie and holines. Shee was ſparing in ſpeach, conſiderate and aduiſed in all her waies and deedes. Shee was as louing and dutifull a daughter to her mother, as euer I knew liuing: which vertue, God recompenced in her life time with the like: that is, with very dutifull and obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t children. She delighted in peace and concord: and if ſhe eſpied any variance toward, either in regard of her ſelfe, or others: ſhe neuer ceaſed nor gaue herſelfe reſt, till ſhee had made vp the breache, by chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reconciliation. She thought much of death, and ſpecially a little before her departing out of this
<pb facs="tcp:12784:22"/>world: wiſhing if it could be by the good pleaſure of God; that ſhee might not out-liue her huſband, but die at the ſame time, which thing accordingly came to paſſe. Mine eares heard it of her in priuate; and therefore I dare the more boldly auoucheit. Shee was not like the fooliſh woman, that pulleth downe the houſe: but ſhee built vp her huſbandes houſe, by wiſe and frugall ordering of her domeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call charges, and maintenance. And yet for all that, ſhe knew how in ſeaſon to open her hand,<note place="margin">A concluſion moſt aptly fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the premi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. Pro. 31.29.30 God of his infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite mercie graunt vs the increaſe of many ſuch good women.</note> and to giue liberally to the needy: vnto whom, ſhe was a nurſing mother.</p>
            <p>So that we may (in regard of the premiſes) truly and rightly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude with the holy Ghoſt. 31 <hi>Pro.</hi> 29 30.31. <hi>ver. Manie daughters haue done vertuouſly:<note place="margin">The vertues of the right chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> knight to manifeſt &amp; confirme the truth of his ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification.</note> but thou ſurmounteſt them all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fauor is deceitfull, and beautie is vanitie: but a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that feareth the Lord ſhall be praiſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Giue her of the fruite of her hands, and let her owne workes praiſe her in the gates.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The outward conuerſation likewiſe of her worthy Huſband, was very Chriſtian, vnblameable, and without iuſt note of reprehenſion.<note place="margin">An example worthy to bee followed of all men: ſpecially of perſons in, ſpecial dignitie &amp; authority a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the reſt.</note>
            </p>
            <p>For firſt of all, whereas (all men know) hee was indued with excellent orname<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of nature and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: yet knew he, how to make himſelfe equall to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the lower ſort. And whereas hee could haue made many affraid (as it is ſaid of <hi>Iob</hi>) yet was hee continuallie fearefull to offend the meaneſt.<note place="margin">An excellent vertue: the true valour of great &amp; mighty me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> In which reſpect, if he had at any time ouerſeene
<pb facs="tcp:12784:22"/>himſelfe: his ſoule was neuer at reſt, till hee had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moued the offence, and ſatiſfied the party. Hee bare a feruent loue &amp; zeale toward the truth, which hee was ready at all times, to defend againſt <hi>Papiſts, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſts, &amp; Hereticks, &amp;c.</hi> as diuers do well knowe, who haue felt the force and weight of his argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts in diſputation. He was bountifull and liberall, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the meaſure of that portion and reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newes that GOD had beſtowed vpon him: as the poore round about him can and wil teſtifie: whoſe ſides were warmed with the fleece of his ſheepe and their empty and hungry ſtomackes, relieued &amp; ſatiſfied of his owne prouiſion. How he carried him ſelfe in his publick calling, concerning the admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of Iuſtice: the worſhipfull magiſtrates, both here and elſ where in this country, can both know and iudge. Yet thus much I know, and dare affirm: that he was carefull to do his duty.<note place="margin">A concluſion not forced but very wel appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</note> And that which is more, and a very ſpecial grace of God in a magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate: hee hated and auoided priuy bribes and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards;<note place="margin">1. Sam. 13.</note> leaſt his eies ſhould bee blinded therewith and his heart corrupted,<note place="margin">God graunt vs many ſuch good Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, euen for the Lord Ieſus ſake: and bleſſe theſe excellent examples to helpe forward ſo gratious a worke of his &amp; ſo neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie for his church. Amen.</note> and ſo turned aſide from iuſtice and equity. So that he might (if hee were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue) make his iuſt <hi>Apologie</hi> for himſelfe, <hi>as Samuel</hi> did <hi>1. Samuel.</hi> 13 in theſe words.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Behold here I am, bare record of mee before the Lord, &amp; before his annointed: whoſe Oxe haue I take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or whoſe Aſse haue I taken? or whom haue I done wrong to? or whome haue I hurt? or of whoſe hand haue I receiued a bribe to blinde mine eies there with, &amp; I will reſtore it you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:12784:23"/>
All this, and the reſt, I ſpeake (God knoweth) not in the way of flattery, to gratifie the eares of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie (as it is the manner of too many in aſſemblies vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch occaſions as this is,<note place="margin">The common abuſe of fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Sermons iuſtly taxed.</note> to make their tongus ſaleable in decking them with ornaments of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation, which are moſt vnworthy of any great commendation) I haue abhorred flattery ſince I knewe the Goſpell, and rather runne into the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie. Neither need I in this caſe to vſe flatterie: ſeeing I may appeale to the conſciences of al them that knew them. Yet did they not want their blemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes and infirmities: all which (I doubt not) are co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered and waſhed away in the precious blood and death of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt. And therefore, ſeing that they both drew in one yoke of obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce;<note place="margin">The vſes of the former ſonota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble an exe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</note> &amp; not only walked hand in ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in the waies of righteouſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes while they liued, but alſo were not much diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the act &amp; inſtant of their death:<note place="margin">1. For chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> conſolation &amp; comfort.</note> what enuy of man? what rage of Sathan? what power of hell can let, but that both of their ſoules are now in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Angels &amp; ſoules of the righteous? triu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phing againſt the deuill, the world &amp; the fleſh, &amp; all their ſpirituall enemies: ſinging praiſe to God with the whole Church, for their creation &amp; preſeruatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> herevpon earth; ſpecially for their redemptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation by the blood of the Lambe: wiſhing the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the number of Gods elect; that the miſeries of the faithfull might haue an end: ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge at the fountaine of liuing waters: wearing longe white roabes, waſhed in the blood of Ieſus
<pb facs="tcp:12784:23"/>Chriſt: fedd and nouriſhed continuallie, with the fruit of the tree of life, beholding the glorious face of their ſweet Lord and Sauiour, whoſe preſence in their life time, they wiſhed and longed for, with teares and earneſt praiers. Finally, they liue &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine in ſuch fulnes of ioy and happines: as to the perfection thereof, nothing ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be added or deſired.</p>
            <p>So that they neede no outward ſolemnities of Buriall, although it bee agreeable to their eſtate; and ſerueth very well for the auoyding of <hi>Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſticall</hi> confuſion. For why? in their life time, they reared vp to themſelues a Tombe in heauen, not periſhing or corruptible, but euer during and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall: not poliſhed by the art and cunning of man; but grauen and commended by the hand of Gods ſpirit. And therefore ſo glorious, as it is not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pleaſant and acceptable to God and his Angells: but alſo maketh co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinualie, for the encreaſe of their owne comfort.<note place="margin">2. For chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſorrow and mourning: yet with godly mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration.</note>
            </p>
            <p>All which, notwithſtanding this their great hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pines, yet is there cauſe, why their death and depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſhould bee lamented and bewailed:<note place="margin">It is the duty of al ſores mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deratelie to mourne at the death &amp; buriall of their friends ſpecially of ſuch as were of beſt imploi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment &amp; vſe.</note> not only generally, but alſo by particular perſons.</p>
            <p>Generally, the Church militant hath great cauſe to lament: that two ſuch excellent and profitable members, are rent from it.</p>
            <p>Particularly, their chlidren haue cauſe to mourn, and ſorrow: for that they want two ſuch excellent Parents, who did ſo tender and loue them as their own ſouls;<note place="margin">Children.</note> and therefore ſought both by exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple &amp; al
<pb facs="tcp:12784:24"/>good meanes, to procure their comfort and good eſtate, in this life, and in the life to come.</p>
            <p>Seruants, for that they haue loſt the gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and direction of ſuch a Maſter &amp; Lady,<note place="margin">Seruantes.</note> as continu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ally expreſſed no leſſe loue and care ouer them then if ſo be they had ben their naturall children: ſo that by their death, they are bereft of many ſweete comforts and helps, which many a yeare, ſome of them inioyed.</p>
            <p>Let the miniſtery of this congregation, mourn &amp; ſorrow:<note place="margin">Miniſters.</note> for that it is diſappointed, and left deſtitute of ſuch worthy Patrons.</p>
            <p>Let ſtudents and fauorers of Learning,<note place="margin">Students.</note> ioine with the fotmer in mourning: ſeeing they ſhall all ſee the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no more in this world, by whome, before times, the receiued co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort &amp; incorageme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in their ſtudies</p>
            <p>Let the Noble and worſhipfull race of Gentry,<note place="margin">Magiſtrates.</note> lay to heart the loſſe of two ſuch familiars, as were moſt faithfull and dutifull to them.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Poore of Den. ham, and in the townes adioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</note>But O yee poore and miſerable of theſe partes, howle yee and cry out: ſeeing they are taken from you, whoſe hands in times paſt were alwaies open to relieue your neceſſities.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Miniſter himſelfe then a chief mourner for them on earth: but now achiefe reioicer with them in heauen.</note>And would to God, mine eies would guſhe out teares, yea riuers of teares; ſeeing the place and ſeats open, now empty and without them whoſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence in times paſt, was comfortable to my heart: where vnto they alwaies bent themſelues, as did appeare, by their readineſſe and willingneſſe to repaire to this place.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:12784:24"/>
Finally, there is cauſe, that all ſhould mourne for the death of ſuch perſons: according to the laudable cuſtome and manner of the Church,<note place="margin">The cauſes of comfort are re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſumed &amp; more fully amplified becauſe they are greater and therfore ought to receiue the deeper &amp; more durable impreſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion, chiefly in the heartes of thoſe that are moſt ſubiect to paſſe boundes in mourning.</note> in all times.</p>
            <p>Yet, leaſt we ſhould paſſe meaſure, and runne into the exceſſe of mourning, wee want not iuſt cauſe to moderate and temper our mourning and ſorrowe: and that not only for that we are not without hope, as were the heathe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> but for far better &amp; more agrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble cauſes. And firſt of all, although they be go<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e, yet haue they left behind them many perſons equall to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in degre &amp; dignity: who are not o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly indued with excellent gifts, but ready &amp; preſt to performe the ſame duties, which they in their life time performed</p>
            <p>As namely, to profeſſe and maintaine the Goſpell,<note place="margin">The 1. cauſe of comfort.</note> ſincerely to worſhip &amp; ſerue the Lord, and to go be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore other in a holy &amp; chriſtian example of life.<note place="margin">A 2. cauſe of comfort.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Againe, it ought not a little to mitigate our ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe, in regard of their departure, becauſe as they honoured God in their life, ſo God hath now hono<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in their death: as appeareth this day not o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly by the ſolemnities of their buriall, but alſo in the great concurſe of all ſorts; who are come toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, euery one according to his place, to teſtifie, what honorable and louing affections they bare to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward them,<note place="margin">A 3. Cauſe of comfort.</note> both in life and in death.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The laſt &amp; full cauſe ſhuttinge vp &amp; perfecting all our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort, againſt all our mourning:</note>Laſtly, that we may at le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth conclud: the greateſt matter of comfort is, that although they haue left vs for a time; yet, ere it bee longe, wee ſhall meete with them in the Kingdome of God. For which purpoſe, becauſe wee know not howe ſodenly the
<pb facs="tcp:12784:25"/>Lord will come either by death,<note place="margin">And thus a ſweete conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of a verie ſweete, godlie, learned, and fruitfull Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon. To God be all the praiſe, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, &amp; glory: &amp; to vs much benefit &amp; ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall edificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, through his moſt gratious bleſsing.</note> or at the laſt iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (as we haue good cauſe to bethinke vs thereof, by the preſent occaſion) let vs not driue off, as the ſlouthfull ſeruant in the Goſpell; or as the fooliſh virgins: but let vs fit our ſelues before hand, for his glorious comming: that is, let vs get oyle in our lamps with the wiſe virgins; and euerie one of vs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haue our ſelues faithfully in our place and calling, by imploying ſuch gifts as we haue receiued of our So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne Lord and Maiſter, to the glory of God, and the benefit of our brethren. And then (no doubt) as the ſecond death, ſhall not hurt vs, ſo ſhall wee enter into our Maiſters ioy: where we ſhal with the ſoules of the righteous, crie continuallie, <hi>Lord Ieſus come quicklie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reu. 22.21.</note> as the ſoules of theſe two perſons doe. And in the end, we ſhal doubtles heare thoſe ſweet words of heauenly entertainement, which Chriſt our Lord &amp; Sauiour, from his glorious throne ſhall pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, to the vnſpeakeable comfort of all the elect: ſaying, <hi>Come ye bleſſed of my Father, inherit the Kingdome prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 25.34.</note> 
               <hi>from the foundation of the world.</hi> Which, the Lord of his infinite mercie haſten: &amp; ſpeedily put an an end to the miſeries of this world, vnder which we doe continually ſigh and groane.<note place="margin">2. Cor. 5.4.</note> And that euen for Ieſus Chriſt his ſake, our onely Redeemer and Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our: to whom, with the Father, &amp; the holie Ghoſt, be rendred and giuen for euer and euer, both in heauen and earth, all poſſible praiſe, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, glory, &amp; immortalitie. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus an ende.</p>
            <closer>Let vs pray.</closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:12784:25"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
